子供[こども]:child/children, 正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness
（ヤサコ）子供のウワサでは
ミチコさんの正体は―
According to rumors told by kids,
Miss Michiko's true identity
イリーガル:illegal, ささやく:to whisper/to murmur|to rumor
イリーガルではないかと
ささやかれています
is whispered to be that of an Illegal.
（フミエ）なんで？
But why?!
Miss Michiko
From the Other Side
黒[くろ]:black|black go stone|guilt, 客[きゃく, かく]:guest/visitor|customer, 客[まろうど, まろうと]:visitor from afar/guest, 連中[れんちゅう, れんじゅう]:company/lot|troupe, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
なんで黒客(ヘイクー)の連中も
一緒なの？
Why should the hacker club come with us?!
生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables
（マイコ）
あら ダイチ君たちは
今も生物部よ
Daichi and his friends are still a part of the Biology Club.
Huh?
部長[ぶちょう]:head (chief, director) of a section or department|head of a (school) club/head of a (school) team, 辞める[やめる]:to resign/to retire/to quit
ダイチ君は部長を辞めただけ
Daichi has only stopped acting as the club president.
大黒[だいこく]:god of wealth|monk's wife, 黒[くろ]:black|black go stone|guilt, 客[きゃく, かく]:guest/visitor|customer, 客[まろうど, まろうと]:visitor from afar/guest
そんな～！
でも 今は大黒(だいこく)黒客の…
No way! But they're in the Daikoku Hackers Club now!
勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily, 名乗る[なのる]:to give one's name (as)|to claim to be|to reveal oneself (as)||, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
それは勝手に名乗ってるだけでしょ
問題ないわ
They just took on another name, you know.
No big deal.
そんな～！
No way...
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, 合宿[がっしゅく]:lodging together/training camp/boarding house
（ヤサコ）
それで 昨日 言ってきたのね
合宿でやるつもりなんだわ
So that's what they were talking about yesterday.
They want to do "it" during the sleepover!
（フミエ）ハッ！
（マイコ）やるって何を？
Do "it"?  What's that?
あっ いえ その…
Oh well, you know...
なんでもないです…
Nothing, really!
（ヤサコ）ねえ フミエちゃん
Hey, Fumie,
昔[むかし]:olden days/former, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 夏祭り[なつまつり]:summer festival
昔は ダイチ君と
一緒に夏祭り行ったんでしょ？
you went to a summer festival with Daichi before, right?
仲[なか]:relation/relationship, 仲[すあい, すわい]:broker/brokerage/brokerage fee, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
なんで仲悪くなったの？
So why aren't you friends anymore?
あいつがバカだからよ
Because he's an idiot.
特訓[とっくん]:special training/intensive training/crash course
そんなことより ヤサコ 特訓よ！
More importantly, Yasako,
special training!
特訓[とっくん]:special training/intensive training/crash course
特訓？
Special training?
戦い[たたかい]:battle/fight/struggle, 備える[そなえる]:to furnish|to have ready|to possess (all that is needed)|, 素振り[そぶり]:behavior/behaviour/manner, 素振り[すぶり]:practice-swinging (sword, bat, tennis racket, etc.), 回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||
（フミエ）戦いに備えて
メガビーの素振り100回！
We need to get ready for battle,
so we're going to practice the megabeam hand gesture one hundred times!
素振り[そぶり]:behavior/behaviour/manner, 素振り[すぶり]:practice-swinging (sword, bat, tennis racket, etc.)
す… 素振り？
J-Just the gesture?
音[おと, ね]:sound|note|fame|
（ハラケン）音… 音だ
A sound...
It's a sound!
What's up, Haraken?
用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|
（デンパ）
何？　ハラケン　僕に用って
Why did you call me?
頼み[たのみ]:request/favor|reliance, 頼み[だのみ]:depending on/dependent upon
（ハラケン）頼みがあるんだ
I need to ask you a favor.
黒[くろ]:black|black go stone|guilt, 客[きゃく, かく]:guest/visitor|customer, 客[まろうど, まろうと]:visitor from afar/guest, 辞める[やめる]:to resign/to retire/to quit
（デンパ）ヘ… 黒客は辞めないよ
I-I'm not going to leave the hackers.
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception, 音[おと, ね]:sound|note|fame|
違うんだ デンパ
こいつの音を聞いてほしいんだ
It's not that, Denpa.
I need you to listen to the sound coming from this.
はっきり:clearly/plainly|to be clear, 聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
僕じゃ はっきり聞こえなくて
I can't hear it clearly.
Oh. Good then.
それならいいよ
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
聞こえる
I can hear it...
Music and...
a human voice.
女の子[おんなのこ, おんなのコ]:girl/daughter|young woman, 女の子[めのこ]:woman/girl, 声[こえ]:voice
女の子の声だ
A girl's voice.
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 貸す[かす]:to lend/to loan|to rent out, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
ねえ これ少し
貸してもらっていい？
Hey, would you mind if I took this for a while?
音[おと, ね]:sound|note|fame|, 聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be, やすい:cheap/inexpensive|calm, やすい:easy|likely to .../have a tendency to ..., 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
なぜだか メタバグの音が
聞こえやすくなる場所があるんだ
Just so you know, there's a place where you can hear metabug sounds more clearly.
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally
うん もちろん
Okay. Go for it.
Okay then, I'll take it with me.
借りる[かりる]:to borrow/to have a loan|to rent, 必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, 返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|
じゃあ借りるね　必ず返すから
I'll give it back to you, of course.
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception
ねえ デンパ
（デンパ）んっ？
Hey, Denpa.
Hmm?
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception
デンパは
なんでダイチの仲間になったの？
Why did you join Daichi's group?
昔[むかし]:olden days/former, いじめる:to tease/to torment/to persecute, 助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|
昔 いじめられてたとき
ダイチが助けてくれたんだ
Well, a long time ago, I was being bullied,
and Daichi came to my rescue.
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), 味方[みかた]:friend/ally/supporter
他の人は知らんぷりしてたけど
ダイチだけ味方してくれた
Everyone else was just ignoring what was happening,
and only Daichi helped me out.
そっか　いいヤツだな ダイチ
I see.
So Daichi is a good kid.
Director,
室長[しつちょう]:section chief/laboratory manager/office head, せめて:at least/at most, せめて:offense/offence/method of attack, 学校[がっこう]:school, 許可[きょか]:permission/approval|to permit, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（オバちゃん）室長
せめて学校だけは許可してください
please allow it. At least at the school.
緊急[きんきゅう]:urgency/emergency
緊急なんです
It's an emergency!
駅[えき]:station, 騒ぎ[さわぎ]:uproar/disturbance
駅ビルの騒ぎは聞いたでしょ？
You've heard about the trouble at the station, haven't you?
廃車[はいしゃ]:decommissioned vehicle|deregistered vehicle|deregistering (vehicle), 場[ば]:place|field|occasion||, 場[じょう]:place/spot/grounds, 騒ぎ[さわぎ]:uproar/disturbance
（一郎(いちろう)）ああ 廃車場の騒ぎもね
Yes, and also about the trouble at the auto graveyard.
It has come to my attention.
随分[ずいぶん]:very/extremely|contemptible, 派手[はで]:showy/loud/gay, 大黒[だいこく]:god of wealth|monk's wife, 苦情[くじょう]:complaint/troubles/objection
随分 派手にやったそうだね
大黒バスから苦情が来たよ
I've received a complaint letter from the Daikoku Bus Company.
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 犯人[はんにん]:offender/criminal
（オバちゃん）
それも同じ犯人なんですよ
It's the same culprit!
管理[かんり]:control/management (e.g. of a business), 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 手を出す[てをだす]:to turn one's hand to|to get involved in|to start a fight
とにかく
管理外には手を出さんでくれ
Anyway,
don't do anything outside your administrative jurisdiction.
すでに:already/too late, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||, 設定[せってい]:establishment/creation|options setting, 済み[ずみ, すみ]:arranged/taken care of/settled
すでにサッチーは入れないよう
設定済みだ
We're already done setting the locations Satchii can't enter.
所詮[しょせん, そせん]:after all, 役所[やくしょ]:government office/public office, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
（オバちゃん）
所詮(しょせん) お役所仕事か…
After all, it's just a job in a municipal office.
間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman), 学校[がっこう]:school
キラバグは 間違いなく
あの学校にあるのに―
Although I'm sure that kirabug hides in that school,
管理[かんり]:control/management (e.g. of a business), 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, ドメイン:domain, 出す[だす]:to take out|to put out|to submit (e.g. thesis)||
管理外ドメインでは手が出せない
I can't make a move outside the administrative boundaries.
やはり:too/also|still, 自身[じしん]:by oneself/personally, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing, させる:to make (someone) do|to allow (someone) to, させる:(usu. followed by a negative form) worth special consideration
やはり 天沢(あまさわ)自身に
見つけさせるしかない
I guess,
all I can do is let Amasawa find it.
鍵[かぎ, カギ]:key|lock, 鍵[けん]:key (of a piano, etc.), 回す[まわす]:to turn|to circulate|to surround||, 始まる[はじまる]:to begin|to happen (again)|to date (from), 逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
（イサコ）ええ 鍵を回したけど
始まる前に逃げられて…
Yes, I turned the key,
but it ran away before I could begin.
反応[はんのう, はんおう]:reaction/response, 遅れる[おくれる]:to be late/to be delayed/to fall behind schedule, 起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen
反応が遅れて起こることが？
Is it possible that the reaction signal is delayed?
やってみる:to have a go/to try and do (something)/to take a chance with something
分かった やってみるわ
I see.
I'll give it a try.
すでに:already/too late, 目くらまし[めくらまし]:smoke screen|camouflage|magic|, 打つ[うつ]:to hit|to strike (noon, etc.)|to beat (rhythmically, e.g. pulse, waves, etc.)||, 打つ[ぶつ]:to hit (a person)/to strike/to beat
すでに目くらましの手は打ってある
I already shot the flashing-eyes thing.
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 夏休み[なつやすみ]:summer vacation/summer holiday
（ウチクネ）マイコ先生
なんで夏休みに入って―
Maiko-sensei,
why did you schedule the sleepover right after the beginning of summer break?
合宿[がっしゅく]:lodging together/training camp/boarding house
すぐに合宿なんですか？
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
ウチクネ先生こそ
なんでいるんですか？
By the way, Mister Uchikune, why are you here today?
生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables, 合宿[がっしゅく]:lodging together/training camp/boarding house
今日は生物部の合宿なんですよ
It's the Biology Club's sleepover, not yours.
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, 困る[こまる]:to be troubled/to be worried/to be bothered
（ウチクネ）マイコ先生一人じゃ
何かあったとき困るでしょ？
I just thought you might have trouble here all by yourself. If something were to happen...
頼もしい[たのもしい]:reliable/trustworthy|hopeful, いただく:to receive/to get|to eat, 予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule
（マイコ）頼もしい男なら
２人も来ていただく予定です
If it's about reliable men,
I already have two of them coming along.
柔道[じゅうどう]:judo, 三[さん, み]:three|tri-, 三[サン]:three, 段[たん]:variable measure of fabric (28.8 cm in width)|300 tsubo (991.74 meters square, 0.24506 acres)|six ken (10.91 m), 段[だん]:step|grade|counter for breaks in written language (or speech, etc.)
１人は…
（教頭）柔道三段です
One is...
Judo, third dan.
教頭[きょうとう]:deputy head teacher/vice principal, 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 参加[さんか]:participation, なさる:to do
（ウチクネ）
教頭先生も参加なさるんで？
So... the vice principal is participating as well?
で もう１人は？
What about the other guy?
頼もしい[たのもしい]:reliable/trustworthy|hopeful, 男性[だんせい]:man/male|masculine gender
頼もしい男性です
He's a very reliable man.
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 参加[さんか]:participation
わ… 私 絶対 参加します！
I'm definitely coming along, too!
Ninety-seven,
（フミエ）97 98 99… 100
ninety-eight,
ninety-nine,
one hundred!
ホント:truth/reality/actuality, 上達[じょうたつ]:improvement (e.g. in skill, ability)/advance|communication of opinions of the general populace to those of high rank
ねえ こんなんで
ホントに上達するの？
Hey, are you sure that we're really going to get better by doing this?
多分[たぶん]:perhaps/probably|generous
多分ね
Probably.
Now we just have to defuse their traps preemptively.
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 前もって[まえもって]:in advance/beforehand/previously, 潰す[つぶす]:to smash|to shut down|to thwart||
さあ 次は あいつらのワナを
前もって潰すだけね
Preemptively?
前もって[まえもって]:in advance/beforehand/previously
（ヤサコ）前もってって？
情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information, 筒抜け[つつぬけ]:being overheard/being leaked (e.g. secrets)|going in one ear and out the other
（フミエ）ダイチの情報は筒抜けよ
I can spy on all of Daichi's data.
If someone challenges me,
挑む[いどむ]:to challenge/to throw down the gauntlet|to pressure someone for sex, 全力[ぜんりょく]:all one's power/whole energy, たたく[たたく]:to strike|to play drums|to abuse||, 潰す[つぶす]:to smash|to shut down|to thwart||
私に挑むなら
全力でたたき潰すまでよ
I'm not going to hold back.
ありったけ:all that one has/all that there is/the whole, メタタグ:META tag, インストール:installation (esp. software)
さあ ありったけのメタタグを
インストールするわよ
Okay then, now we have to install as many metatags as possible.
That Space hasn't healed since.
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through
（ヤサコ）
あれから 空間 壊れたままね
あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals, 通る[とおる]:to go by|to run (between)|to go indoors||
あそこも通るの？
Should we go there too?
I don't know...
（フミエ）さあ？
（ヤサコ）
ねえ こんなウワサ知ってる？
Have you heard that rumor?
That Miss Michiko comes out of the cyberfog...
霧[きり]:fog/mist|spray, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places
霧の出る所には
ミチコさんが出るんだって
Cut it out!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, 苦手[にがて]:poor (at)/weak (in)|dislike (of), 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
やめてよ！
私 苦手なのよ その手の話
I really hate those kinds of stories!
Me too.
苦手[にがて]:poor (at)/weak (in)|dislike (of)
（ヤサコ）
私も… 苦手ってほどじゃないけど
Well, maybe not to the point of hating, but...
It's my weak point.
ほとんど:mostly/nearly/practically, 弱点[じゃくてん]:weak point/weakness/shortcoming
（フミエ）
私は もう ほとんど弱点よ
When I hear a ghost story,
怪[かい]:mystery/wonder, 談話[だんわ]:a talk/conversation, 力が抜ける[ちからがぬける]:to grow weak/to become weak/to lose strength
怪談話 聞くと
力が抜けちゃうのよね
When I hear a ghost story,
I lose all my strength...
弱点[じゃくてん]:weak point/weakness/shortcoming, 突く[つく]:to prick|to poke|to use (a cane)||, 突く[つつく]:to poke (repeatedly, lightly)|to peck at (one's food)|to peck at (someone's faults, etc.)|
（ナメッチ）この弱点を
突かない手はありませんね
We have to take advantage of this weak point.
Your pet sure is useful.
使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET
（ガチャギリ）
使えるな お前のペットは
Yup, it's a spy.
筒抜け[つつぬけ]:being overheard/being leaked (e.g. secrets)|going in one ear and out the other
（アキラ）はい 筒抜けです
Listen, Akira.
なあ アキラ
（アキラ）はい
Yeah?
You're not a double agent, are you?
おめえ:you (formerly honorific, now sometimes derog. term referring to an equal or inferior)|presence (of a god, nobleman, etc.), 二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 重[おも]:chief/main|main secondary or supporting role (in kyogen), 重[え]:-fold/-ply, スパイ:spy
おめえ
二重スパイじゃねえだろうな？
N-Not at all!
ち… 違いますよ
Now that you mention it, he usually stays behind while we're in action.
行動[こうどう]:action/conduct/behaviour, はぐれる:to lose sight of (one's companions)/to stray from|to miss (one's chance to ...)
（ダイチ）そういや
いっつも行動中 はぐれるしな
That's because I'm a slow walker...
足[あし]:foot|leg|gait||, 足[そく]:counter for pairs (of socks, shoes, etc.), 遅い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|
そ… それは足が遅いから
And why did you join our club and not your sister's?
姉貴[あねき]:elder sister, グループ:group (usu. of people)
（ナメッチ）お前
なんで姉貴のグループじゃなく
側[そば, そく]:near/close|third person, 側[がわ, かわ]:side (of something, or taking someone's side)/part|(watch) case
俺っちの側に入ったんだ？
Well, that's obviously...
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, 皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything, 憧れる[あこがれる]:to long for/to yearn after/to admire
そ… それは もちろん
皆さんに憧れてです
because I respect you guys!
Hey, don't try to fool us, you fourth-year!
おい ６年をナメんなよ ４年！
（アキラ）ぐああ～！
作り笑い[つくりわらい]:forced laugh/forced smile, なんざ:what star sign? (astrology)/what constellation?, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
作り笑いなんざ
10年 早(はえ)んだよ！
You're a long way from getting to laugh behind our backs, brat!
Spill your guts out!
（ナメッチ）本当のこと言えよ！
いい… 言います 言います
本当のこと言います！
I'll talk! I'll tell you the whole truth!
As soon as possible...
一刻[いっこく]:minute/moment|stubborn, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
い… 一刻も早く
"As soon as possible," what? Say it!
一刻[いっこく]:minute/moment|stubborn, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
一刻も早く… なんだ？　言え
If I don't distance myself from you guys as soon as possible,
一刻[いっこく]:minute/moment|stubborn, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 距離[きょり]:distance/range, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
一刻も早く距離を取らないとお～
my sister is capable of
お姉ちゃん[おねえちゃん]:familiar form of "older sister"|form of address for young adult female, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death), 吸い取る[すいとる]:to suck up/to absorb/to squeeze (money)
お姉ちゃんに
人生を吸い取られそうでえ～
draining my life away!
Sorry for bullying you.
いじめる:to tease/to torment/to persecute, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
いじめて悪かった
I understand how you feel.
気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
（ナメッチ）その気持ちは分かるぜ
As men, we need to help each other out.
同士[どうし, どし]:fellow/mutual/companion, 助け合う[たすけあう]:to help each other/to cooperate
男同士 助け合おうな
Oh, Denpa.
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception
（ハラケン）あっ デンパ？
Yes.
4-4-2-3?
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
４４２３… って聞こえるの？
Is that what you hear?
Welcome
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||, 生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables, 合宿[がっしゅく]:lodging together/training camp/boarding house, ようこ:mythological fox spirit
（マイコ）
第１回 生物部合宿へ ようこそー！
to the first Biology Club sleepover!
Yay!
（生徒たち）イェーイ！
The vice principal will join us this evening!
教頭[きょうとう]:deputy head teacher/vice principal, 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
今日は教頭先生も一緒でーす
（一同）イェーイ！
Also,
呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||, 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
それから呼んでもいないのに
ウチクネ先生も来てくれました
although nobody invited him,
Mister Uchikune came with us too!
I came, too...
来ちゃった…
（生徒たち）ええー！
And one more person
親[おや]:parent|dealer (in cards, mahjong, etc.)|founder|, 親[しん]:intimacy|close relative|pro- (e.g. pro-American, pro-Japanese, etc.), 御[ご]:honorific/polite|honorific suffix, 御[ぎょ]:honorific affix|honorific prefix, 参加[さんか]:participation, 予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule
あと１人 親御さんから
参加されるご予定なんですが…
from the PTA was supposed to come, but...
Forget waiting for him!
ケーキ:cake, 入刀[にゅうとう]:cutting the cake (at a wedding)
そんなの待ってないで
ケーキ入刀しようぜ
Let's cut the cake!
Daichi,
わきまえ:sense/discretion/knowledge, なさる:to do
ダイチ君 もう６年なんだから
わきまえを知りなさい
you're a sixth-grader now, so act more mature!
Maiko-sensei says "Wakimae," which means to reason and act maturely.
Daichi responds with a pun: "Waki" (armpit) and "Mae" (in front of).
Here's my reason!
ワキまえ～！
（男子たちの笑い声）
Stop, Daichi!
（マイコ）ダイチ君 もう！
Daichi's really the worst.
最低[さいてい]:least|worst|awful|, 騒がしい[さわがしい]:noisy/boisterous|turbulent (era, etc.)
（アイコ）ダイチ君 最低
（ヤサコ）騒がしいのね
He's so noisy.
By the way, his family name, "Sawaguchi", sounds just like "noisy".
苗字[みょうじ]:surname/family name
苗字 沢口(さわぐち)だしね
And here's how I act!
Another pun: Maiko-sensei said "wakimae wo shiri-nasai" or "you have to know"; he plays on "shiri", that also sounds like "ass".
尻[けつ]:ass|rear|acupuncture point|, 尻[しり]:buttocks|undersurface|last place|
尻まえ～
Hey! Ow, ow, ow!
アイタッ アイタタタ…
Hey, Daichi.
（ダイチの父）こら ダイチ！
D-Dad, why are you here?!
父ちゃん[とうちゃん, とっちゃん]:dad/daddy/papa
と… 父ちゃん なんで ここに？
I invited him.
呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||, 我[われ, わ]:I|oneself|you|, 我[わが]:my/our/one's own, ながら:while/during|while, 名案[めいあん]:good idea
お呼びしたのよ
我ながら名案だわ
And it seems it was a good idea.
That's right, Teach.
とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light), 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
そのとおりです 先生
When I heard it was about a sleepover, I came immediately!
強化[きょうか]:strengthening/intensifying/reinforcement, 合宿[がっしゅく]:lodging together/training camp/boarding house, 飛ぶ[とぶ]:to fly/to soar|to jump, まいる:to go/to come|to be defeated
強化合宿と聞いて
飛んでまいりました
親善[しんぜん]:friendship/goodwill/friendly relations, 合宿[がっしゅく]:lodging together/training camp/boarding house
いえ 親善合宿…
N-No, it's just a convivial sleepover...
I'll take good care of disciplining the boys.
男子[だんし]:youth/young man, しごく:to draw through one's hand/to stroke (e.g. a beard)|to work someone hard, しごく:very/extremely|top
男子は この私が
ビシビシしごきます
Get ready, you brats!
覚悟[かくご]:resolution/resignation/readiness
お前ら覚悟しろ！
The basis of a sleepover is hand gestures!
合宿[がっしゅく]:lodging together/training camp/boarding house, 基本[きほん]:foundation/basis/standard, 素振り[そぶり]:behavior/behaviour/manner, 素振り[すぶり]:practice-swinging (sword, bat, tennis racket, etc.)
合宿の基本は素振りだ
Do the gestures!
素振り[そぶり]:behavior/behaviour/manner, 素振り[すぶり]:practice-swinging (sword, bat, tennis racket, etc.), 回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||
素振り1000回！
フォーム:foam
バカもん！　フォームは こうだ！
Idiot!
It's like this!
セイ セイ セイ…
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa
（マイコ）お… お父さん それは？
S-Sir, that's...
卓球[たっきゅう]:table tennis/ping-pong, 小[しょう]:smallness|short month (i.e. having fewer than 31 days)|elementary school||, 小[こ]:small|slightly less than|somewhat|, 中高[なかだか]:convex, 中高[ちゅうこう]:middle and high school|medium and high (level), 一筋[ひとすじ]:one long straight object (e.g. strand of hair, beam of light, wisp of smoke)|a single bloodline|earnest|
卓球です
私は小中高と卓球一筋です
It's ping-pong!
Every single year of school, all I did was ping-pong!
父ちゃん[とうちゃん, とっちゃん]:dad/daddy/papa, 卓球[たっきゅう]:table tennis/ping-pong, 生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables
と… 父ちゃん
卓球部じゃなくて生物部なんだよ
D-Dad...
This isn't the ping-pong club, it's the Biology Club!
生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables
生物部？
Biology Club?
ほとんど:mostly/nearly/practically, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables
ほとんど電脳生物部ですけど
Actually, we work with cybermateria...
てっきり:surely/certainly/beyond doubt, 卓球[たっきゅう]:table tennis/ping-pong
てっきり 卓球部かと…
For some reason, I thought it was ping-pong.
どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 勘違い[かんちがい]:misunderstanding/wrong guess
どんな勘違いよ
What a silly misunderstanding.
生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables, 素振り[そぶり]:behavior/behaviour/manner, 素振り[すぶり]:practice-swinging (sword, bat, tennis racket, etc.), どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), フォーム:foam
生物部の素振りは
どんなフォームだ？
So what gestures does the Biology Club practice?
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, もくろみ:plan/scheme/project, 成功[せいこう]:success/hit
（教頭）どうです？
先生のもくろみは成功ですか？
What do you think?
Was yours a good idea?
（マイコ）さあ？
I don't know...
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 遊ぶ[あそぶ, あすぶ]:to play|to mess about (with alcohol, gambling, philandery, etc.)|to be idle||, 遊ぶ[すさぶ]:to grow wild/to rage|to do something one enjoys, きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
でも こうして一緒に遊べば
きっと前のように戻れます
But if they play together like this,
I think they'll be able to be friends again.
時期[じき]:time/season|soon
（教頭）しかし なぜ この時期に？
But why did you choose this season?
仲直り[なかなおり]:reconciliation/make peace with
（マイコ）
だって 今 仲直りしなきゃ
Well, if they don't make up now,
小学校[しょうがっこう]:primary school/elementary school/grade school, 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 夏休み[なつやすみ]:summer vacation/summer holiday, ケンカ:quarrel/brawl/fight, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
小学校最後の夏休みが
ケンカで終わっちゃうわ
their last summer in elementary school will end with them fighting.
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 優しい[やさしい]:tender/kind/gentle
そうだったんですか！
マイコ先生 なんてお優しい
So that's why!
Maiko-sensei, you're so gentle!
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 寝袋[ねぶくろ]:sleeping bag, 閉じる[とじる]:to close (e.g. book, eyes, meeting, etc.)/to shut, 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||
（マイコ）
ちゃんと寝袋は閉じて寝るのよ
Don't forget to close your sleeping bags before going to sleep.
（生徒たち）はーい
Yes, ma'am.
やっぱり:too/also|still, 子供[こども]:child/children, 眠る[ねむる, ねぶる]:to sleep (not necessarily lying down)|to die|to lie idle (e.g. of resources)|
やっぱり子供ですわ
もう眠ってます
As expected, the kids
are already sleepy.
じゃ やりますか
It's our turn now!
町内会[ちょうないかい]:neighborhood association/neighbourhood association, おごり:luxury/extravagance|treat (i.e. at somebody's expense), おごり:arrogance/haughtiness/conceitedness
（ダイチの父）
ヘヘヘッ 町内会のおごりです
This is a present from me, the head of the town committee.
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 弱い[よわい]:weak/frail/delicate, 酒[さけ, ささ]:alcohol/sake
（教頭）今日はマイコ先生が弱い
お酒はありませんからね
There's no alcohol, since Maiko-sensei can't take it well.
弱い[よわい]:weak/frail/delicate
（マイコ）ヤダわ…
そんなに弱くないですって～！
Come on!
I'm not that  weak!
邪魔[じゃま]:hindrance|to visit (somebody's home)|demon who hinders Buddhist training
こいつ… 邪魔すんな
Damn...
Stop interfering!
ポイント:point, 譲る[ゆずる]:to turn over/to assign|to yield
このポイントは譲らねえ
I'm not gonna give you this point!
どう？
How's it going?
まあ やるだけはやったわ
I did all I could.
ところどころ:here and there/some parts (of something)/several places, 変[へん]:strange|unexpected|change||, ゆがみ:strain/distortion/deformation, ゆがみ:hairdo
ところどころ
変なゆがみがあるけど…
But there's some strange disturbances in places...
果たし合い[はたしあい]:duel, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
（ダイチ）
おい 果たし合いの前に話がある
Hey!
I have something to tell you before the duel.
とっとと:quickly/at once/right away
何よ とっととやりましょうよ
What now?
Let's get this over with!
せっかく:stone burial chamber, せっかく:with trouble/at great pains|rare, 肝試し[きもだめし]:test of courage/dare, 盛り上げる[もりあげる]:to pile up/to heap up|to stir up, からにする:to empty/to vacate/to evacuate
せっかくの肝試しだからな
盛り上げてからにしようぜ
As you know, this is a trial of courage.
Let's warm up first.
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
まずは怖い話でもしようや
For starters,
let's begin with a scary story.
ミチコさんとかな
Like the one about Miss Michiko.
そ… そう来たか
R-Really?
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
ウヒヒヒヒッ 怖いのか？
Are you scared?
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
こ… 怖いもんですか
Wh-Why should I be?!
早速[さっそく]:at once/immediately/without delay, わたくし:I/me|private affairs
じゃあ 早速
わたくしめから１つ
Well then, I'll start with mine.
普通[ふつう]:general|normally|local train, 女の子[おんなのこ, おんなのコ]:girl/daughter|young woman, 女の子[めのこ]:woman/girl
（ダイチ）ミチコさんは
どこにでもいる普通の女の子でした
Miss Michiko was
a very ordinary girl, like any girl you'd see anywhere.
可愛い[かわいい, かわゆい]:cute|dear|cute little, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET
でも ある日
可愛がっていた電脳ペットが
But one day, her beloved cyberpet
突然[とつぜん]:abrupt/sudden/unexpected, 走る[はしる]:to run|to travel (movement of vehicles)|to hurry to||
突然 走り出しました
suddenly ran off.
ミチコさんは見ました
Then Miss Michiko saw it.
真っ黒い[まっくろい]:pitch black/deep black, 生き物[いきもの]:living thing/animal, 道路[どうろ]:road/highway, 向こう[むこう]:opposite side|over there|the other party|
真っ黒い生き物が道路の向こうで
A jet-black creature
on the other side of the street calling, "Come, come..."
いでる:to go/to come
“おいで おいで”を
しているんです
止める[とめる]:to stop|to park|to prevent||, 止める[やめる]:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 道路[どうろ]:road/highway, 飛び出す[とびだす]:to jump out|to appear (suddenly)|to protrude|
ミチコさんが止めるのも聞かず
ペットは道路へ飛び出して
The pet didn't listen to Miss Michiko telling it to stop,
and ran across the street.
画像[がぞう]:image/picture/portrait, ゴチャゴチャ:jumble/mix up, 混じり合う[まじりあう]:to be mixed together/to be blended/to intermingle
車の画像と
ゴチャゴチャに混じり合って
Its graphics were scrambled by the car's,
消える[きえる]:to go out/to vanish/to disappear, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
消えてしまいました
and then it disappeared.
数[しばしば]:often/again and again/frequently, 数[かず]:number/amount, 後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
数日後 ペットのことが
忘れられないミチコさんは
A few days later,
Miss Michiko still couldn't forget about her pet,
so she returned to that intersection.
交差点[こうさてん]:crossing/intersection
交差点に行きました
グチャグチャ:pulpy/soppy/sloppy, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET
すると グチャグチャになって
死んだはずのペットが
At that moment,
her pet, which was supposed to be shattered and dead...
道路[どうろ]:road/highway, 向こう側[むこうがわ]:other side/opposite side/other party
道路の向こう側で
Guess what?
いでる:to go/to come
“おいで おいで”を
しているじゃありませんか
It was calling, "Come, come..." from the other side of the street.
Miss Michiko couldn't stop her legs from moving on their own.
足[あし]:foot|leg|gait||, 足[そく]:counter for pairs (of socks, shoes, etc.), 勝手[かって]:one's own convenience|surroundings|convenience||, 踏み出す[ふみだす]:to step forward/to step forth|to start
ミチコさんは 自分の足が
勝手に踏み出すのを
止める[とめる]:to stop|to park|to prevent||, 止める[やめる]:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel
止められませんでした
グチャグチャ:pulpy/soppy/sloppy, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
ミチコさんは
グチャグチャになってしまいました
Miss Michiko was shattered into pieces.
かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse), メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 全く[まったく]:really|indeed|good grief (expression of exasperation), 傷[きず, キズ]:wound|chip|flaw||
ところが かけていたメガネだけは
全く傷がなかったそうです
Surprisingly, it's said that only the glasses she was wearing
were completely undamaged.
その後[そのあと, そのご]:after that/afterwards/thereafter, 交差点[こうさてん]:crossing/intersection, メガネをかける:to wear glasses/to put on glasses
その後 交差点でメガネをかけると
Since then,
it's said that when you put your glasses on at that intersection
you can see her.
端[そば, そく]:near/close|third person, 端[はし, はじ]:end (e.g. of street)|beginning|odds and ends, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
その端っこに見えるそうです
いでる:to go/to come
“おいで おいで”をしている
ミチコさんが
"Come, come," calls Miss Michiko.
場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
その場所こそが…
That particular place
is said to be the site of many urban legends:
都市[とし]:town/city/municipal, 伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore, はざま:interval/space|valley, 交差点[こうさてん]:crossing/intersection
都市伝説に聞く
はざま交差点なのです
the loophole nexus.
One of those is enough.
一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree
それは一度でいい
（ナメッチ）へい
Okay.
The version you told is the most common one.
話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., もっとも:most/extremely, もっとも:but then/although|reasonable, 類型[るいけい]:type/pattern|similar type, 的[てき]:-like/typical, 的[まと]:mark/target
（ハラケン）その話は
もっとも類型的なやつだね
例えば[たとえば]:for example/for instance/e.g., だいぶ:lengthy (of a book, etc.)/voluminous|most (e.g. most part), だいぶ:considerably/greatly/a lot, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
例えば ヒワタでは
だいぶ違うらしい
For example, the story in Hiwata is quite different.
Apparently, in Hiwata, Miss Michiko
ヒワタのミチコさんは
ended up going to the "other side" while at school.
学校[がっこう]:school, あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener), しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
学校の中で あっちへ
行ってしまったそうなんだ
On that day, Miss Michiko arrived late to school.
遅刻[ちこく]:lateness/late coming, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
ミチコさんは
その日 遅刻をしてしまった
When she got to the third floor, it was dead quiet.
階[かい]:storey|stairs|stage (in chronostratigraphy)|, 階[しな]:article|quality|flirtatiousness, 着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow, シーン:scene/sight, シーン:silently (as the grave)/quietly (as in death)
３階に着いたら シーンとしている
異変[いへん]:unusual phenomenon/unusual event/abnormal event, 気づく[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise
そこでミチコさんは異変に気づいた
Then she realized that something very strange was going on.
Although it was still morning,
朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||, 窓[まど]:window, 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 夕焼け[ゆうやけ]:evening glow/red sunset/afterglow (of sunset)
まだ 朝なのに
窓の外が夕焼けなんだ
it was afternoon light pouring through the windows.
時計[とけい, ときはかり]:watch/clock/timepiece, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation, 教室[きょうしつ]:classroom|department|single-room school, のぞく:to remove/to eliminate|to exclude, のぞく:to peek (though a keyhole, gap, etc.)|to look down into (a ravine, etc.)
ミチコさんは時計を確認しようと
教室をのぞいた
Miss Michiko peeked inside a classroom to check the time.
But...
時計[とけい, ときはかり]:watch/clock/timepiece
でも時計はなかった
there was no clock.
Not only that...
どころ:particle used to indicate that what precedes it is an extreme example and strongly negates it, 生徒[せいと]:pupil
それどころか
生徒も１人もいなかった
there wasn't even a single student.
It was the same in the next classroom,
隣[となり]:neighbor (neighbour)/next to (esp. living next door to), クラス:class
隣のクラスも その隣のクラスも
and in the classroom after that.
Miss Michiko was scared and tried to get out,
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid, 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|
ミチコさんは怖くなって
外に出ようとした
but...
階段[かいだん]:stairs/stairway/staircase, 下りる[おりる]:to descend (e.g. a mountain)|to alight (e.g. from bus)|to step down||, 階[かい]:storey|stairs|stage (in chronostratigraphy)|, 階[しな]:article|quality|flirtatiousness, 着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow
ところが階段を下りても下りても
１階に着かないんだ
The stairs went down and down, but she could never reach the first floor.
どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 下りる[おりる]:to descend (e.g. a mountain)|to alight (e.g. from bus)|to step down||, 高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive, 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
どんなに下りても高さが変わらない
No matter how far down she went, the bottom never got any closer.
Miss Michiko thought the glasses must've been causing it,
メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 幻影[げんえい]:phantom/vision/illusion, 違い[ちがい]:difference/discrepancy, 気づく[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise
ミチコさんは
メガネの幻影に違いないと気づいて
so she tried to take them off.
メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 外す[はずす]:to unfasten|to remove|to leave|
メガネを外そうとした
But she didn't have her glasses on.
メガネ:spectacles/glasses
ところが メガネはなかった
At that moment,
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||
いつの間にか
電脳の体だけになっていたんだ
her body had become a cyberbody.
Miss Michiko cried out loud in fear.
恐怖[きょうふ, くふ]:fear/dread/dismay, あまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 叫ぶ[さけぶ]:to shout/to cry|to clamor (for or against)
ミチコさんは恐怖のあまり叫んだ
At that moment,
無人[むじん, ぶにん]:lack of help|unmanned/uninhabited, 教室[きょうしつ]:classroom|department|single-room school
すると 無人だったはずの
教室の中から
from a classroom that should have been empty...
Guess what? She heard children's voices.
生徒[せいと]:pupil, 声[こえ]:voice, 聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
生徒たちの声が
聞こえてくるじゃないか
Miss Michiko felt like she had just woken up from a dream,
夢[ゆめ]:dream, 覚める[さめる]:to wake|to become sober|to come to one's senses, 気になる[きになる]:to be on one's mind|to feel like|to fancy, 教室[きょうしつ]:classroom|department|single-room school, のぞく:to remove/to eliminate|to exclude, のぞく:to peek (though a keyhole, gap, etc.)|to look down into (a ravine, etc.)
ミチコさんは夢から覚めたような
気になって教室をのぞいた
So she peeked inside the classroom,
and there,
教室[きょうしつ]:classroom|department|single-room school
すると 教室の中は…
inside the classroom,
she saw jet-black wraiths swarming around.
形[かたち, よう]:form/shape|visage, 形[かた, がた]:shape|collateral|obverse of an old "zeni" coin, 真っ黒い[まっくろい]:pitch black/deep black, 生き物[いきもの]:living thing/animal, ひしめく:to clamour/to crowd/to jostle
人の形をした真っ黒い生き物が
ひしめいていた
Miss Michiko finally figured it all out.
ようやく:finally/at last|barely, ようやく:summary/digest, 気づく[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise
（ハラケン）ミチコさんは
そこで ようやく気づいたんだ
In no time at all,
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||
いつの間にか 自分の体も
she herself
had also become a jet-black wraith.
真っ黒い[まっくろい]:pitch black/deep black, 生き物[いきもの]:living thing/animal, 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
真っ黒い生き物に
変わっていたことに
Huh?
あれ どうしたの？　みんな
What's wrong, everyone?
Oh, there's also another version from another region...
地域[ちいき]:area/region, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
そうだ 別の地域での話も…
E-Enough.
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, 十分[じっぷん, じゅっぷん]:10 minutes, 十分[じゅうぶん]:plenty|division into ten|perfectly
や… やめて もう十分よ
I've had enough.
I-I agree.
とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light)
そ… そのとおりだ
面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant
（ハラケン）えっ 面白いのに
But it's fun!
L-Let's start right now...
済む[すむ]:to finish|to merely result in something less severe than expected|to feel at ease|, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||
ささ… さっさと済ませて
（フミエ）早く寝ましょう
...so we can get to sleep quickly.
But even from an anthropological point of view, it's really interesting!
民俗学[みんぞくがく]:folkloristics (formal study of folklore), 的[てき]:-like/typical, 的[まと]:mark/target, 面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant
いや 民俗学的に見ても面白いから
Please...
ぜひ！
Cut it out already!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（２人）もう やめて～！
反応[はんのう, はんおう]:reaction/response, 始まる[はじまる]:to begin|to happen (again)|to date (from)
ハッ… 本当だ　反応が始まった
So it is true!
It started to send out a signal.
うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious, 探知[たんち]:detection
ここでは うまく探知できないな
This isn't a good spot for detection.
ポチ タマ 来い
Pochi.
Tama.
Come.
やはり:too/also|still, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||, しかたない:it can't be helped/it's inevitable/it's no use
やはり入れないか… しかたないな
So there's no way they can enter.
I have no choice then.
決まる[きまる]:to be decided/to be settled|to look good in (clothes), 回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||
（ダイチ）き… 決まったか？
２人ずつで ３回 行く
S-So it's decided, right?
We'll climb three times in groups of two.
周[しゅう]:Zhou (dynasty of China)|perimeter|counter for laps or circuits
５人だから
１人だけは もう１周だ
But since there's only five of us, someone will have to make an extra round.
回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||
俺が２回 行く
I'll go to twice.
代わり[かわり]:substitute|stand-in|compensation||, 代わり[がわり]:substitute for ..., 分け前[わけまえ]:share/portion/quota, 割[わり]:rate|profit|assignment||, 増し[まし, マシ]:better|more|increase
その代わり
メタバグの分け前 １割増しだ
But in exchange, I want 10% more on my metabug share.
割[わり]:rate|profit|assignment||, 安い[やすい]:cheap/inexpensive|calm
（ダイチ）そ… それでいい
１割なら安いもんだ
It's okay.
10% is cheap enough.
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||, まわる:to turn/to revolve|to visit several places, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
悪いわね ２回まわってもらって
I'm sorry that you have to climb twice.
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
フミエちゃんほど
怖がりじゃないから
I'm not as scared as you.
人数[にんずう, ひとかず]:the number of people|many people/a large number of people, 合う[あう, おう]:to come together|to fit|to be profitable|
（アイコ）ちょっと待って
人数が合わないわ
Hey, wait.
We don't have the same number.
黒[くろ]:black|black go stone|guilt, 客[きゃく, かく]:guest/visitor|customer, 客[まろうど, まろうと]:visitor from afar/guest
黒客は５人でしょ？
でも こっちは４人よ
There are five of you hackers, right?
But there's only four of us.
ホント:truth/reality/actuality
ホントだ
Oh, you're right.
不利[ふり]:disadvantage/handicap/unfavorable position
ちょっとダイチ！
これじゃ こっちが不利じゃない
Hey, Daichi!
We're at a disadvantage!
見過ごす[みすごす]:to let go by/to let pass/to overlook, 抜く[ぬく]:to extract|to do something to the end|to surpass||
見過ごしてたな
こっちを１人 抜くか？
I hadn't noticed that.
So should we put one of our people out?
シフト:shift, 変える[かえる]:to change/to alter|to reform
でも ワナのシフトは
変えられないぜ
But we can't change the traps' shift.
（マイコ）私でどう～？
What about me?
話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
（マイコ）話は聞いたわ
I know everything.
私も行くうぅ～！
I wanna go, too!
せっかく:stone burial chamber, せっかく:with trouble/at great pains|rare
せっかく せっかく…
And I...
仲直り[なかなおり]:reconciliation/make peace with, 合宿[がっしゅく]:lodging together/training camp/boarding house
あなたたちを
仲直りさせようと合宿したのに！
planned this sleepover for you to be friends again!
臭う[におう]:to be fragrant|to stink|to glow|
臭っ！
Crap!
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 酔う[よう]:to get drunk|to feel sick (e.g. in a vehicle)|to be elated
先生 酔ってるんですか？
Teacher, are you drunk?
んっ？　これは…
Aren't these...?
駄菓子[だがし]:cheap sweets, なかなか:very/considerably|by no means (with negative verb), いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good
いやあ～
駄菓子もなかなかいけますな
The dagashi sure are good, too!
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, ウイスキー:whisky/whiskey, ボンボン:bonbon, 酔っ払う[よっぱらう]:to get drunk
（ダイチの父）
先生 ウイスキーボンボンで
そんなに酔っ払って…
Who could've imagined that Maiko-sensei would get drunk on whiskey bonbons?
ウイスキー:whisky/whiskey, ボンボン:bonbon, 泥酔[でいすい]:dead drunk
この人 ウイスキーボンボンで
泥酔しとる
She's dead drunk on whiskey bonbons.
（マイコ）
それなのに それなのに…
And yet...
Yet...
黙る[だまる]:to be silent, 肝試し[きもだめし]:test of courage/dare, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
何よ 黙って肝試しするなんて！
How could you do this trial of courage without me?!
If you wanna do it, then let your teacher in too!
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 交ぜる[まぜる]:to mix/to stir/to blend, なさる:to do
だったら 先生も交ぜなさい
どういう:somehow/how/in what way, 理屈[りくつ]:theory/reason
どういう理屈だよ
By what principle should you be involved?
酔っ払い[よっぱらい]:drunkard, 理屈[りくつ]:theory/reason, 通ずる[つうずる]:to be open (to traffic)|to flow (liquid, current)|to be understood||
酔っ払いに理屈は通じないのよ
ア～ハハハハ！
There's no principle that works with drunk people!
独身[どくしん]:bachelorhood/single/unmarried, 引き取る[ひきとる]:to take over|to take charge of|to retire to a private place
この独身女 誰か引き取れよ！
Please, someone take this single woman away!
肝試し[きもだめし]:test of courage/dare
レッツ 肝試し～！
Let's do the trial of courage!
すでに:already/too late, 分離[ぶんり]:separation/partition/detachment
すでに分離したのか？
So has it separated already?
やはり:too/also|still, 急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten
やはり来たか 急がなくては
So she came.
I must hurry.
近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly
よし 近くにいるな
Perfect.
It's around here somewhere.
ハァ ハァ…
うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious, 探知[たんち]:detection
（オバちゃん）なんだと？
うまく探知できなくなった
What's this?
I can't detect anything any more...
（２人）ハァ ハァ…
I see.
なるほど:I see/That's right!/Indeed, かく乱[かくらん, こうらん]:disturbance/perturbation/derangement, 目的[もくてき]:purpose/goal/aim
（オバちゃん）
なるほど かく乱が目的か
So their objective was to create a disturbance.
オーケー:OK
オーケー
Okay,
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 遠慮[えんりょ]:reserve|declining|forethought, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
じゃあ こちらも
遠慮なくやらせてもらうわ
then I won't hold back either.
低次元[ていじげん]:low-level/trivial|low-dimension, 戦い[たたかい]:battle/fight/struggle
なんか低次元な戦いになってきたわ
Somehow,
this battle has gotten really cheap...
くっ… まだ これからだ
There's still more to come!
腕[うで]:arm|skill/efforts, 腕[かいな]:arm (esp. upper arm)|counter used to measure the thickness of round objects, 精いっぱい[せいいっぱい]:the best one can do/one's best effort|with all one's might
（オバちゃん）
私の腕では これが精いっぱいだ
That's the best I can do
with all my skills.
バレる:to leak out (a secret)/to be exposed (a lie, improper behaviour, etc.) (behavior), 責任[せきにん]:duty/responsibility (incl. supervision of staff)|liability, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
バレたら責任問題だな
If I get caught, I'll be held responsible.
A girl's laughing voice...
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
ま… まさかミチコさん？
D-Don't tell me it's Miss Michiko—?
慌てる[あわてる]:to become confused (disconcerted, disorganized, disorganised)/to be flustered|to be in a hurry, 仕掛け[しかけ]:device|trick|(small) scale||
バカ 慌てるな！
これはヤツらの仕掛けだ
Idiot! Don't jump to conclusions!
It must be a trick from those brats!
ハァ…
んっ？　マジかよ…
You have to be kidding...
仕掛け[しかけ]:device|trick|(small) scale||
これって ダイチ君たちの仕掛け？
This must be a trick of Daichi's!
光る[ひかる]:to shine/to glitter/to be bright, ちっちゃい:tiny/little/wee, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
今 光るちっちゃい人みたいなの
見ませんでしたか？
Did you just see a small, human-like shining figure?!
Huh?
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, からかう:to ridicule/to tease/to mock, 魂胆[こんたん]:ulterior motive/plot|complicated circumstances
あ～ こいつ
先生をからかおうって魂胆だな
Hey, you.
Are you trying to fool your teacher?
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
先生！
Teacher!
やっと:at last/at length|barely, 着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
ハァ… やっと着いた
（ガチャギリ）早く戻ろうぜ
We've finally arrived!
Let's head back quickly!
先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.)
（ヤサコ･マイコ）お先に～！
Bye-bye!
急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten
急ぐぞ！
Let's hurry!
（ヤサコ）ハァ…
（フミエ）ど… どうだった？
So how did it go?
楽勝[らくしょう]:easy victory
ら… 楽勝よ
It was a piece of cake!
女の子[おんなのこ, おんなのコ]:girl/daughter|young woman, 女の子[めのこ]:woman/girl, 笑い声[わらいごえ]:laughter
あの女の子の笑い声は
ちょっとビビッたけどね
I was just a little scared by that girl's laughing voice.
女の子[おんなのこ, おんなのコ]:girl/daughter|young woman, 女の子[めのこ]:woman/girl
えっ 女の子？
A girl's?
It was easy.
大した[たいした]:considerable/great/important
た… 大したことなかったぜ
女の子[おんなのこ, おんなのコ]:girl/daughter|young woman, 女の子[めのこ]:woman/girl, 笑い声[わらいごえ]:laughter, 怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
あの女の子の笑い声は
怖かったですけどね
But I was scared by that girl's laughing voice.
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception
よ… よし 行くぞ デンパ
（デンパ）うん
P-Perfect.
Let's go, Denpa!
女の子[おんなのこ, おんなのコ]:girl/daughter|young woman, 女の子[めのこ]:woman/girl
女の子？
A girl's?
やはり:too/also|still, アルファ:alpha, 型[かた, がた]:model|type|mold (mould)||, イリーガル:illegal
やはり アルファ型の
イリーガルだわ
As I thought,
it's an alpha-type Illegal.
反応[はんのう, はんおう]:reaction/response, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
だが 反応は終わっている
But the signal stopped.
キラバグは どこだ？
Where's the kirabug?
少女[しょうじょ, おとめ]:little girl/maiden|female between 17 and 20 years old (ritsuryo period), 暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher
あの少女の暗号だ　こっちか？
This is that girl's encode...
Is she here?
モニター:(computer) monitor, 探知[たんち]:detection, 以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, たどる:to follow (road)/to pursue (course)/to follow up
モニターで探知できない以上
これをたどるしかない
Since I can't detect anything from my monitor,
all I can do is follow this!
イヤ～！
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
頑張ったわ フミエちゃん
You did great, Fumie!
さあ 行こう ハラケン
Let's go, Haraken.
Oh, okay.
頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
あとは頼んだ… ぞ
I leave the rest...
to you.
ようし:(physical) appearance (of a person)/one's face and figure, ようし:blank form|sheets of paper/sheet of paper, 遅れ[おくれ]:delay/lag/postponement, 取り戻す[とりもどす]:to take back/to regain/to get back
ようし！　遅れを取り戻すぞ
All right!
Let's take back the lead!
N-No doubt it's one of Daichi's tricks...
仕業[しわざ]:deed (esp. negative)/act/action, きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly
ダ… ダイチ君たちの仕業よ きっと
Haraken?
ハラケン？
頭痛[ずつう]:headache
頭痛が…
My headache...
光[ひかり]:light|illumination|happiness||
あの光…
That light...
（サッチー）ボク サッチー
Me Satchii!
やっちまった… 行くぞ！
Damn, he did it...
Let's go!
学校[がっこう]:school
なんでサッチーが学校に？
Why was Satchii inside the school?
ハァ ハァ ハァ…
Four...
Two...
Three...
Kanna!
カンナ？　カンナなの？
Is this Kanna?
交差点[こうさてん]:crossing/intersection, 北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, 大通り[おおどおり]:main street, 西[にし]:west, 西[せい]:Spain
（カンナ）交差点を北に
最初の大通りを西に
At the north end of the Crossroads...
take the first big street to the west.
番目[ばんめ]:indicates position in a sequence|divisions of a kabuki performance, 小道[こみち, しょうけい]:path/lane|small diameter, 入り口[いりぐち, いりくち]:entrance/entry/gate
３番目の小道が入り口
The entrance is at the third small street.
北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 進む[すすむ]:to advance|to precede|to make progress||, 進む[すさむ]:to grow wild/to run to waste, 最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, 小道[こみち, しょうけい]:path/lane|small diameter, 東[あずま, あづま]:eastern Japan (esp. Kamakura or Edo, from perspective of Kyoto or Nara)|east|six-stringed Japanese zither|, 東[ひがし, ひむかし]:east
北に進んで 最初の小道を東に…
Then proceed north.
なさる:to do
さあ こっちに来なさい
分かるでしょ？
All right,
come to me.
You know why, don't you?
ここにいるわよ あなたの仲間が
I'm here.
I'm on your side.
結合[けつごう]:combination/union|bond
私と結合するのよ
Now join me:
ミチコ！
Michiko!
Preview
Next time
on Dennou Coil:
Kanna's Diary
See you next time!
次回[じかい]:next time (occasion), 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, コイル:coil
（ヤサコ）
次回 「電脳コイル」
日記[にっき]:diary/journal
〝カンナの日記 〞
楽しみ[たのしみ]:enjoyment/pleasure|anticipation
お楽しみに